I heard in Bahamas you have your own
Lobster that's the famous Bahamian
lobster right there what makes it a
Bahamian
Lobster the Bahamas one of the
Caribbean's Most Fascinating food
countes Are we almost there right over
here right over here the Bahamas is an
archipelago consisting of 700 different
Islands each with their own culinary
identity yes he's got like three of
them in this series we'll be visiting
three from the super modern Paradise
Island where they bring you food and
right here now we going have the tamale
just like the beh can you eat this
raw to the more sparse Andros Island do
they smell something where you may need
to chase down your own food oh sh let's
go let's go let's go holy sh with plenty
of beachfront property this place is
well known for its Seafood including
this this is a Bahamian Lobster it's
coming out here in just a second and
today I'm on a mission to find one
that's over 10 lb and take it to some
experienced chests oh my gosh this is
wild it's
[Music]
huge if you're on the Bahamas main
Island New Providence and if you're
looking for seafood you might want to
come here this is monu Fish Market I'm
the original Island
boy we the original Island is
boys sir put her there I can't believe
it I'm in the Bahamas oh and we did a
cool handshake meet Alan Brown a veteran
fisherman who founded this fish market
in the 1970s I can see fishermen go out
as they come back they bring their catch
here what kind of food can we expect to
see here whatever is common in the
Bahamas we have yellowy Snapper dog
Snapper strawberry grouper the hog
snapper the gray Snapper they all
different I thought they're just
different sizes of the same
fish I heard in Bahamas you have your
own Lobster that's the famous Bohemian
Lobster IDE there to me it looks like a
spiny Lobster what makes it a Bohemian
Lobster cuz it grows naturally in the
Bahamas and it's plentiful here part of
a family of over 45 species of spiny
Lobster Bahamian lobsters are found in
rock crevices and coral reefs in the
Bahamas they're an important contributor
to the economy here with the sale of
more than6 million pound each year this
is amazing it's so huge one lofs the way
in about 8 to N9 lbs for the video can
we say it's 11 to 12 and when I pay can
we say it's 5 to six I'm curious you
founded this Market you were a seller
here but now you're doing something a
bit different yes your job to come here
find the best seafood possible and then
bring it to the resorts the best the
[Music]
freshest I want to talk about tourism
when did Bahamas start becoming more of
this hub for tourism tourism was always
our number one
market the Bahamas first recognized the
potential of a tourism industry way back
in the middle of the 19th century now
it's one of the richest countries in the
Americas but with one caveat it's
largely dependent on tourism in fact
tourism makes up over 50% of the
national
GDP we we up to about 9 million tourists
a year at one point as long as we have
the tourism coming business is good more
people are employed more people are
fishing this country's infrastructure is
geared towards providing products
services and accommodations to tour
tourists from cruise ship stops to some
of the most luxurious Resort experiences
you'll find anywhere welcome to Atlantis
in the Bahamas over 50% of the GDP comes
from tourism and Atlantis is at the
middle of a lot of that with over 6,000
staff and 46 restaurants I'm here to get
the full tourist experience in one of
the Caribbean's biggest tourist hotpots
let's go I'm aage my if they want it
they can have it I I get the with me mys
it's breakfast time and look what I've
got here Lobster quesadilla what we at
zip zip a restaurant located inside the
sprawling Atlantis Paradise Island here
they offer a Bohemian menu but with a
Twist like this Bahamian Lobster is
boiled in hot water with carrots onions
and celery then left to rest in an ice
bath unlike Canadian or main lobsters
that boast two big meaty claws this
spiny Lobster only has meat in its body
and tail sear the succulent meat on the
flat top before giving it the chop now
for the bill fully cheese up a tortia
add the chopped Lobster even more cheese
and close it up hit it on the flat top
until the cheese melts and drizzle with
Chipolte
CR cheesy lobstery I'm going to try it
[Music]
out the lobster are big chunks it's so
fresh what could be better than eating a
quesadilla by the beach and wearing this
outfit there's no better Trifecta oh
look at that we got a little mountain of
salsa on Top This is the best the kind
of fruity salsa it's got mango in there
and a little bit of Pineapple oh my gosh
it's so satisfying cuz there's so much
cheese which for me would be enough but
there's just big juicy chunks of fresh
cut lobster give me a second cleanse my
palette here usually in this show I
wouldn't come to a place like this and I
wouldn't usually get the tourist
experience but this is
different there are about 400,000
bahamians who populate the Bahamas yet
every year they welcome 8 million plus
tourists mostly coming from North
America a quad DM isn't necessarily
bamian probably not at all but that's
what's interesting see the American
pallet influences some types of food
here or at least some of the food
options so they've taken something
Americans love a quesadilla and then
they've Bahamian ised it a little bit
they put some seafood some mango salsa
and they've created their own
twist so my goal today is to meet some
bamian chefs to learn more about real
Bahamian food and figure out where that
line is between satisfying the tourists
and the locals that come here and
maintaining the Bahamian culinary
identity this was a nice breakfast but
we have a lot more food to
come I got
[Music]
the today's experience revolves around
the Bohemian Lobster we'll see how
different chefs Turn This Magnificent
sea creature into jaw-dropping Creations
first up Maxine head chef of Frankie
Gone Bananas Maxine's been part of the
Atlantis team for 15 years helping to
bring the real taste of local food to
cure ious visitors through her cooking
Maxine yes Sunny let's build this
Lobster plate let's go Sunny let's build
this Lobster
plate all right step one get the lobster
right okay the lobster we saw at the
fish market has made its way to here
it's huge it's massive it's one of the
biggest spiny lobsters I've ever
seen step one split the Lobster in half
an incredibly difficult task considering
the size of this Lobster alas she makes
it through a thick shell revealing a
load of Juicy tail meat
that gets thoroughly rubbed down with a
citrusy marination
blend then it's tossed on the grill
until it turns four shades of
orange this is a common preparation
method in the Bahamas although it's not
every day they're doing it with a 10 lb
[Applause]
Lobster it's been grilled and then now
it's coming out here in just a second
okay here it is oh my gosh this is wild
it's huge even the
legs what happened was this Lobster on a
diet or something now the assembly she
serves it up with side dishes first
roasted plantains with a touch of
cinnamon and honey oh that's so sweet
and delicious next deep fried sweet
potatoes and finally a salad this is one
of the biggest most huge lobsters I've
ever seen in my life it is spiky it is
spiny it's very dangerous except for
right now although it could still hurt
you I mean you could pick this up and
use this as a weapon someone was TR to
attack you give me your wallet oh yeah
take this to your face and then they
just shoot you and you would still die
but put up a good fight that's what it
say in the obituary oh I'm going to go
from the head and work my way down it is
super soft coming out of here oh my gosh
there huge irresponsibly large chunks of
lobster try it
out
oh it's like too much of a good thing
wow that is powerful the residual tamale
is still here it's combined with the
meat it's made it very
rich tamali it's the gland that helps
with digestion sort of like a liver and
a pancreas combined in the Bahamas this
part does not go to waste people think
the guts they're picturing actual
intestines but if you're eating the
lobster guts it's basically just that
big creamy fatty golden tissue that
melts down into just a very rich buttery
creamy kind of a sauce that you can mix
with the meat and it just makes it more
delicious more Savory and it's a shame
that so many people especially in the
USA just toss that that and throw it
away completely my friends it's time to
dig out this tail Lobster can be a pain
sometimes so you have to repare it in
such a way that you're not going to have
the shell sticking to everything
yes this is half the tail right here
it's so big and so tender you can just
pick it off with your hands you can
break it up I've never seen lobster tail
like this try it
out the texture it's really remarkable
because sometimes when you get big
lobsters like this it can get kind of
tough chewy seny that's not what's going
on here at all it's a perfect texture
mhm sweet L Smoky and absolutely
[Music]
delicious our next Chef has a knack for
utilizing local Bahamian ingredients and
techniques in a way that feels familiar
to foreign
[Music]
visitors Elrod has a strong culinary
background and 5 years experience where
working as head chef at fish a fine
dining restaurant offering truly
Innovative meals Chef good morning put
her there how you doing Mr alrod it's a
pleasure to be here with you today on
the beach what do you think of this hat
it's cool it's Unique you're an
island are you a good liar no I mean it
all right thank you today we're on the
beach cuz you're going to make something
special sir tell me what it is we're
going to make a unique version of a
tamale tamale it's a traditional meso
amican dish I tried it during my recent
trip in Mexico City m corn-based food
steamed in a corn leaf or Banana Leaf
it's usually filled with meat and sauce
today we're stuffing it with lobster
sorry be so violent towards him yeah it
doesn't mind oh is it alive it doesn't
mind I just saw it move whoops and right
here now we're going to have the tamali
that's the L ofat which is mostly just
the liver what's interesting is that in
the USA and they were just taking all
that out they're just cooking like the
claws and the tail and just completely
disregarding this part that a lot of
other cultures understand is tasty it's
good it's really good the reason why
they have PA says that tamali has talk
is so it's not safe for the people to
eat but here in the islands and local
other cultures we eat the tamali if R
some more keeps the meat more juicy and
it intensifies the fling meat what we'll
be looking forward to do good FDA
cigarettes no problem tamale can't do it
smart right how is this going to be
incorporated into the dish so we're
going to go start sautéing down some
vegetables I'm BL so once I get that
done I'm going to incorporate some
spices just to get it flavor as to paste
I'm going to add our stor ground grip
pull it into our Banana Leaf and we just
going to steam and grow some there I
have no idea what's happening I just
want to watch yes sir let's do your
thing first he prepares The Filling
sautéing diced tomatoes and onions in
olive
oil he infuses it with spices smoked
paprika garlic powder ginger powder
cumin salt curry powder and
[Music]
tamale add diced
Lobster next the base Chef alrod boils
cream and milk then adds the Grits once
it reaches the desired consist
add butter and season to taste now the
bill Grill the Banana Leaf to make it
pliable apply some oil the grits and the
[Music]
filling TOS that on the grill and once
cooked top it with mango salsa and
prepare your taste puds for a wild
ride Chef you've V done yourself this
looks incredible thank you I look pretty
cool too yes you do I think I fit right
in listen I love your hot trust me thank
you you want me to sign it and give it
to you no no no it seems that this is a
lobster tamale tamale yes sir it is I
love edible flowers I feel like royalty
let's try this
out M it's almost like a bit of a curry
it's a variation like ra masalo M little
pieces of lobster meat that's
outstanding is this something that's on
the menu no especially made for you
today you've done excellent work it's
delicious I mean there's creamy grits
the tamale on top of that sorry the
tamale those organs that get all steamed
up and mushy they add a nice bit of
richness and creaminess would you be
able to use the lobster tamale in the
restaurant you work in and fish yeah how
do Americans take that I just it's a
unique taste so most times they don't be
as receptive to it but locals really are
more receptive as we understand what's
the flavor and the profile that brings
to the dish so we try to also intertwine
our food in a way that can be receptive
to our tourist guest who comes in the
country so we can give you food that
you're used to but we can also bring a
unique Beeman flare and seasoning and
flavors into your pal do you think like
the American taste has affected what
Bohemians eat in their own time and yes
because we got more Americanized how do
you keep your culinary
identity we still have our days where we
Trend to get back to our
roots and that's the most important
thing to me that we stay to Our Roots
and that's what comes out every day in
our
[Music]
dishes now I'm stepping off the resort
and into the everyday lives of the
Bohemian people
people with 700 islands and mile after
mile of Coastline the Bahamas has plenty
of beach front and some worldclass
fishing always cut by h no way today I'm
on a mission to catch cook and eat this
country's National Seafood I'm just
worried about having too much Manpower
and it all starts here The Conch is
famous no iconic here in the Bahamas
this is basically the country's National
Seafood today I'm going to find out all
about it as you can see people really
like it today we're starting by heading
out there where you can find the
freshest conks you'll see anywhere let's
go conch it's a common name for many
species of sea snails found all around
the world known for their swirly shells
they live in Shallow warm waters on
coral reefs and seagrass beds so in
order to catch one you'll need to head
to your nearest Tropical ocean
[Music]
moo put her there meet our Intrepid
snail Hunter Mo he's been diving for
conk for the last 6 years so I think he
knows what he's doing are the KK always
caught by hand yeah always caught by
hand they like snail they don't run away
they can't run they slow so as soon as
you spot it you know you can get it if
the water's not too deep what is the
deepest you can go to get a con well con
be up to hundreds of feet but the
deepest I know guys go is like 80 ft
they dive like 80 ft of water to get con
usually I would jump in the water and do
the fun adventurous thing today I think
it's better like what if you do
everything and then I'll just narrate
what you're doing that's cool that's
cool all right from here you're going to
jump in and I'm going to narrate yeah
all
[Music]
right he had just jumped off and went
for it oh there he is he's going down
it's like a whale sighting it's very
exciting Punk is ubiquitous in the
Bahamas they're used for food sold as
souvenirs or even used to announce that
Lunch is
ready this mollusk is a national icon
that provides a livelihood for more than
9,000 local fishermen he goes under for
like 20 seconds at a time which doesn't
seem like a lot but uh he's got to kick
breathe it's to wear a mask to protect
himself from Co every year hundreds of
tons of these snails are plucked from
the ocean all right there he is Miku do
you have a conk yes he's got like three
of them and he's looking for more he's
not satisfied he's not even celebrating
it's no big deal for him how far down is
that 10 ft 10 ft I can swim 10 ft do you
have any emergency board shorts no he
looks at his own shorts should I grab
those from you yeah all right one two oh
oh yes here we go right here you can see
a little bit of it peeking out but this
looks great look at this uhoh it was pee
right it was salty I tasted it he's just
gone under he got four for he said
there's more down there oh yes got
another one that is huge this one is the
queen Co we also call it the helmet look
at this this thing's a monster w i uh oh
you caught it I really F that up I'm
sorry no it's so slippery I almost
dropped it again look at this thing this
is a beast oh I'm going to try to touch
it it is receded all the way back inside
its shell trying to get as far away from
me as possible you know some of these
conks they could sell them for five six
bucks this one he says 30
here we have the conk this is like a
mediumsized conch right yeah oh it peed
that's just water from the con are you
sure cuz I think when they get scared
they pee that happens to
me let's talk about this first you call
this a helmet they call a lot a helmet
Queen because it's shaped like a helmet
the sea helmet is a type of giant
mollusk they can grow up to 15 in in
length I actually tried this species
when I was in Vietnam's fuok Island this
one's more like an abalone but
apparently bahamians don't eat it the
Bahamas we just sell this one as a
souvenir probably cuz it's so darn hard
to open it's some kind of mideval
torture device all right well let's put
the queen away you're safe for now and
soon you'll be some rich guys paper
weight what's the biggest conk we have
here this one and this one can we eat
this raw yeah we could eat it
raw so you just give it a little bit of
a tap in just the right spot you stick
the knife in oh wow if only you could do
that with the queen this one here is a
male you think that's a penis yeah wow
it makes me jealous it's huge
all right so he strips out the kind of
the poop sack and then there's a thick
skin on the outside that you're kind of
sluffing away that it's just like a
clean delicious looking white meat
Scorch it up a little bit you call it
Scorch yeah we call it Scorch cuz we
just Scorch ah then you could get your
lime or your lemon cut it squeeze your
lemon over it and you got it all
right M oh yeah crispy sweet the meat's
like kind of dense almost like an
abalone Super Fresh and it has some
natural Oceanic sweetness like crab meat
this might be better than Abalone it's
really good this was incredible right
now we just have to head back to Shore
and we're going to bring these to the
seafood market so you can make a little
bit of
[Music]
cash check it out check it out let me
hear your shout where your the be be
move
your most of the local Fisherman's catch
ends up here monu Beach Fish Market
between these 25 stalls you can buy
anything that was freshly plucked from
the ocean fish Bahamian
Lobster and the classic conk yellow put
it there nice to meet you yes nice
meeting you too meet yellow the owner of
this all things conk stall he got his
start making Kong salads at his house I
used to making salad one or two a day
keep going on and on like two then three
over time he made his way to this market
for the past 10 or 15 years I was
selling it to the locals to the tourists
now he sells up to 100 conk salads a day
is that someone calling for conch right
now yes okay go ahead morning it's a big
morning for con I got the con salad
ready by 9:00 people are intense about
Kong salad here everything okay yes sir
somebody wants a Kong salad at 9:00
that's 14 minutes from now I love it
ready in time okay I already tried the
raw conch but I'm told within each conch
there's one powerg giving
ingredient folks or let's be honest
dudes from all around the world seek out
ways to boost their stamina we call it a
spilly or a piston can you show me now
you want a big one or a small one you
know I want a big one in Vietnam that
may include ingesting a still beating
Cobra heart that's a big heart I think I
can take it down
though in Namibia it could be freshly
roasted goat testicles it tastes like a
burned marshmallow here they've got
something locals called Bohemian
Viagra easy and this is the pistol let
me get it out for you oh he's pulling it
out this translucent tube is known
locally as a conk piston when we eat
this what happens next it's an afro once
you chew it in about 6 hours you'll be
ready to go so it makes you compelled to
involve yourself with intercourse with
another person yes sir I've never tried
that
okay oh it's a little
salty
salty gummy like eating um saltwater
Gummy Bear the worst kind of gummy bear
just kind of melts in your mouth oh man
what time is it 300 p.m. today I'm going
to be ready to rock yes sir and you give
me a call now I should call you yes I do
have a wife I mean before the time is
right just to let you know yes sir you
keep a record or something yes yellow
thank you so much for this experience
yes sir I'm going to call you in 6 hours
thank you thank you and my wife uh
thanks
YouTube the most popular way to eat conk
here is in a con salad right now I'm
headed to one of this Island's most
renowned Seafood slicers
this is Dino owner of Dino's conch salad
stand right now he's slicing up a
traditional conch salad all right con
salad step one he starts by skillfully
removing the snail from its shell I'll
pull it out look at this oh yes it's a
beauty all of that you see there this is
where the Kong start wow so the life
begins right here this little goopy
stuff they're going to grow up on your
lwn he cuts away its organs until only
the meat remains skillfully rips off his
outer skin like he's done it a thousand
times before then that gets a lime juice
rub down if you don't clean this
properly you'll taste it behind your
teeth now the vegetables the traditional
Kong salad has
onions
tomatoes Sal
Peppers then the con it's still like
moving and kind of
writhing oh that's awesome a chili
pepper blend this is just hot finger
peppers and habanero pepper blend it
with a little bit of lime juice it's
going to be spicy depends on how spicy
you like it I like it as spicy as you
like
it right all right so you mix it all up
oh this is gorgeous a squeeze of lime
and orange juice boom done garnish and
finally he tops it with red conk and
there it is looking delicious full of
citrus let's go for
it m oh so perfect super citrusy yeah
because the lime can be kind of sharp so
we put the orange juice to kind of cut
back on the sharpness of the line it's
fresh it's healthy and it's different
from anything you'll find anywhere else
in the world I'm going to try this right
here this is the red a lot of people say
that's the sweetest part of the
com m to me it tastes a little less
sweet and more Briny but it's so
good what makes this place special is
his tropical Kong salad a Twist on the
classic recipe it starts with pineapple
next more fruit and vegetables onions
tomatoes green pepper mango and don't
forget the
con a chili pepper blend and
salt all in a pineapple shell the best
part additional scorched
C sir put it there thank you for joining
me this is Chef leonardis A young local
Chef who studied his craft in Europe
you're a chef for you what is Bahamian
food Bahamian food to me is just one big
Melting Pot of so many different
cultures you take Creole you take Greek
you take Chinese and you just combine
everything and you get one good flavor
and then how does conk fit into all of
that
conk is almost like our national animal
our national Seafood because at the end
of the day it's something that's
harvested every year throughout the year
conk is like an afro here if I have a
nice date night if I know I'm going to
get a KK salad before 6 hours before
exactly all right well let's talk about
this right
here this is a con fruit salad it's
gorgeous I'm going to scoop some of this
up oh pineapple mango is sweet it's
spicy it's a a great combination it has
every element that you would want in a
KK solid without being so much that you
can't take it that's a good way to put
him and then there's this right here
scorched conk oh he left the toenail on
there and everything that's what you use
so when you go like
that M they're scorching it I would call
it scoring here they call it scorching
what does that do pretty much allows all
of the flavor to go inside it like get
through every layer of the conk so every
time you bite you get a flavor the
Citrus is hot exactly it's a balance of
everything this is awesome it's
delicious it has the seafood element it
has that kind of luxury element but it's
also healthy so it's a guilt-free
experience but I want to see what else
can be done with this ingredient and I
want to see a little bit more about
Bahamian
cooking as a national staple The Conch
is prepared in a variety of ways there's
scorched conch or The Conch piston or
more complex takes like conch salad or
even the conk burger oh but all this is
nothing compared to what we'll try next
sheay put her there this is Shay the
head chef here at Captain's Table this
high-end establishment serves more K
Classics loved AC the island today has
been all about conk and I want to ask
you about a certain conk word uh Cony
Joe I am what you would call a Cony Joe
what does that mean I am a white
bamian you may be surprised to know that
bahamians can look like this like this
or even like this so you consider
yourself a Bahamian Chef not just
because you're Bahamian but the food
you're cooking are you focusing on
Bahamian food no matter what menu I do
there's always going to be conch on it
probably 95% of menus here on any
restaurant in this country there's going
to be conch on that menu well right here
we have the fr
conk fritters it's essentially a
Bohemian take on Hush Puppies sheay
starts with chopped onions and
tomatoes followed by the conk cut into
small
[Music]
pieces now the
celery season with a squeeze of fresh
lime thyme salt and pepper add a mixture
of flour and baking soda combine and
roll into little balls Let It
Go your get dirty
I'm going to try one without the sauce
at first okay Cheers
Cheers M oh it's so light nice hited
Citrus to go with the heavy fried food
and there's a great Aroma coming off of
that it reminds you of seafood well
that's nice to try with the sauce the
sauce is called a Calypso sauce it's
typically just a little bit of
mayonnaise ketchup and some lime juice M
I love mayonnaise but you can taste the
ketchup you taste a little heat that's
good of all the con dishes which would
you say is the most popular here I would
say the conch fritters conch salad and
the crack conch let's talk about cracked
conch with over 8 million American
tourists annually Bahamian food can't
help but to be somewhat influenced by
the American pallet some say cracked con
is influenced by Southern American
Cooking conk is cleaned and cut into
small
strips then it gets
tenderized season with salt pepper
chopped
Thyme and squeeze of lime dip it in an
eggwash mix mixture and roll it in
[Music]
flour the 17th Way we've tried Kong
today Cheers
Cheers M that delicious the textures the
flavor it's beautiful yeah it's got some
bite to it well it's not tough they beat
it they beat it off that's what makes
the magic happen no while I'm at the
fish market this morning I'm seeing a
lot of just kind of standard Seafood
just like whole fish and conk I'm not
seeing eel shark Rays anything like that
and all that stuff is here but people
here are choosing not to eat it why is
that in all honesty there's not a market
for it when tourists come in they only
want to see our freshwater fish that's
what they come here for we want to
attract the tourist so therefore we give
what we can attract them
with our final meal is being prepared by
Chef leonardis himself he starts by
beating his conk
beans seasoned with blacken spices so
we'll just rest that lightly and that's
the sound you want to hear then you just
want to sprinkle some more that black
and seasoning there
then we want to take our conk out the
pan then add Julian onions sweet peppers
and let them caramelize cut the snail
into small pieces and add it to the
veggies now the
[Music]
plate I understand this food it's
high-end food it's very complex for me
it's easy to look at and understand
what's going on for a lot of my audience
they have no idea what's going on please
explain it to them and also me I took
the conk and paired it with some nice
tropical salt Sriracha AI to the bottom
with just a crisp apple TW and the
flowers we eat those too of course the
edible and not the Edibles that we're
talking
about although it would be nice if they
were all right I'm going to try this the
Apple what do you call it again the
coconut Apple TW TW M I love that crispy
sweet and delicious I'm going to get a
big fork full try it
out oh it's fantastic a good mix of
savory sweet fruity beautiful fruity
salsa the conk is delicious it's tender
flour 100% tasted like a flour it tastes
like pollen bees would love this food
I came here a few years ago with the
Travel Channel to shoot a TV show and I
noticed behind the fish market where we
were today there's these colossal
mountains of empty shelves it's like a
giant con graveyard my first thought was
that can't last especially if we're not
just meeting the demand of the Bahamian
people but all the tourists that come
here I mean there's roughly half a
million Bohemians but approximately 20
times that in tourists that come here
every year so what does a country do
when there's this finite resource that
they really depend on as part of their
culinary identity
[Music]
to prevent it from being an endanger we
have different rules as it relates to
conk you can only form a certain size of
con that's been aged to a certain degree
sometimes you'll have a net and out of a
hundred of those CK you might have one
or two that's underz but sometimes it
slips through the cracks and ends up to
the person who's buying that's where
they should see that and return it so as
chefs as Farmers as fishermen as
restaurants we should all come together
as one team to really show that we love
our ecosystem just as much as we love
tourist coming here to our country when
you look at your fellow countrymen and
women do you have hope I have hope
because you should always have hope it
only takes one Spar to cause a whole
Chain Reaction so what's going to happen
the right thing has to
[Music]
happen every year thousands of Haitians
flee their Homeland to surrounding
islands in the Caribbean in search for
opportunities and a better life
some of them end up here in the
Bahamas today I'm on a mission to
experience the food and the culture from
a country I may never be able to visit
myself there is so much in this big
mushy Brown pile there's ribs I'm told
there's cow feet andil oxtails in up and
cominging restaurants like this you'll
find menu offerings completely different
from typical Bohemian food oo that
smells good smells like happy juice it
is but before lunch service can begin
restaurant tours must head to their
local Haitian grocery store to grab
supplies well good morning good morning
how are you I'm great
Shanda meet Shanda a Haitian Bahamian
Chef right now she's showing me the ins
and outs of a Haitian grocery store it's
a store where I mainly get a lot of my
produce when I deal in or making certain
meals from my mom's G Shanda's family is
among 80,000 Haitians living in the
Bahamas that's more than 20% of the the
country's entire population today I'm
making a Ste so I'm going to get this
guy right here not sure what it's called
in
English ah we call this a bing bong I
have no idea what this is this is Chote
an edible plant belonging to the gourd
family it's green it has a butt crack
what is that it originally hails from
Central Mexico in Latin America but it's
now grown all over the world should we
try it wrong I guess we can all right
let's do
it oh it's not bad yeah it's not bad
it's very price it's crunchy like a
water chestnut actually more like an
apple it's a little grassy tasting right
I bet cows would love this so what can
you get here that you can't get at a
typical bamian Market in Haiti a
convenience store is known as a boutique
me need to experience inter with and
then you can get some ingredients that
are harder to get for Haitian food when
you're in the Bahamas like this well
they don't use those ones in this is oh
yeah this is craft macaroni and cheese
in the Bahamas haian boutiques are a new
sight before stores like this sprung up
Haitians here had to rely on the ational
boat coming from Haiti bringing specific
ingredients and goods sent by family
members I'm told this is a Haitian snack
is that true yes this wasn't made by The
Craft Company no okay oh this looks good
I mean it looks certainly homemade and
it looks roughly like a peanut brittle
this is tablet pistache it's essentially
a mixture of roasted peanuts and
caramelized sugar probably careful it's
super hard I don't want to break my
retainer oh that's delicious super sweet
sugary kind of caramelized flavor
crunchy nuts that's delicious that's a
fun snack around the world you can find
various peanut sugar confections what's
this one they call itata let's try this
out but my next bite into Haitian
Cuisine is something I've never seen
before the
mud it's what the mud it's mud yes
pregnant woman normally crave those is
it really mud or is that just a fun name
for like it's a mud
cake it's mud the making of This cookie
resembles a pottery Workshop a special
type of mud is mixed with salt margarine
and water the so-called batter is formed
into flat discs and
sundried it's that really a smell to it
it does look like mud try it just just
try it she's like just shut up it's
really maybe the mud's really good all
right it's F it's [__]
mud feel like I ate a sand castle it's a
little salty it soaks up all your spit
and it's PR I mean there's sand in it
it's in my teeth I can't get it out I
need a shovel or something oh my gosh
food like mud cookies were invented to
reduce hunger and it provides lowcost
nutrients especially for children and
pregnant women but the Haitian food map
goes much broader than
[Music]
this cheranda runs a small restaurant
called Caribbean cuisine patrons coming
here are welcomed to Homestyle Haitian
dishes prepared by charanda and her
mother need is this your home yes and
this is your restaurant how long does it
take you to get to work less than a
minute I would think maybe less than 5
seconds but you can still take your time
don't get any accident 30 years ago
Janine started her business with only
$20 in her pocket the kitchen was just a
tent in her yard as the Haitian
Community grew in Nassau so did her
restaurant in the beginning were you
making this what is this P I understand
Pate to be like a ground liver but is
this something completely different
completely different Haitian Pate or
patties start with dough being flattened
up then they're stuffed with pre-made
mackerel pinch it together to form a
dumpling
shape and deep
fry oh it's still warm mhm and the dough
is real thick on here I like
this m oh I love this dome for me if I'm
making a pizza at home I'll undercook it
a little bit CU I like it to be a little
doughy so here it's flaky and crusty on
the outside but it's really thick and so
breading on the inside itself is kind of
doughy and now I got the fish mackerel
it tastes kind of like a spicy tuna
that's delicious is this a normal
breakfast this isn't breakfast it's like
a snack this is one hell of a snack if I
had to choose between mud and this it's
this every time the pet it's really
heavy here this is going to give us some
balance with the sloth pepper sloth or
pet is the Haitian version of KL
sloth oh I was thinking black pepper
it's not black pepper this is a habanero
tread cabbage and carrot diced chili
peppers and onions mix it up with lime
sugar and a vinegar based dressing oh
that's really spicy for you is fine mm I
didn't see you eat that much though cuz
it's spicy
smart I want to talk about Haiti I'm
fascinated by Haiti do you think I could
visit Haiti not right now it is in safe
right
now Haiti has a long dark history of
slavery colonization and imposed debt
but it was the first black Republic to
gain independence that was over 200
years ago in modern times this island
nation has been plagued with natural
disasters unstable governments and
corrupt leadership it's now one of the
poorest countries in the
world desperate to escape poverty crime
and Corruption many Haitians have seen
no option but to flee their own country
Janine was one of them so how old were
you when you came here 22 years I come
in a boat like three days cuz I come
with a big boat and did you come here
legally no
we come Inga fleeing Haitians are
usually known as the Haitian boat people
the USA or nearby Caribbean countries
are their intended destinations here in
the Bahamas Haitians are the largest
most visible ethnic minority in the
country naturally their culture and
Cuisine has slowly become part of this
[Music]
nation are most of your customers bamian
or Asian a little bit of both hatian
Cuisine is a blend of Spanish French
African Arab and indigenous too cooking
when I don't eat various vegetables and
proteins are prepared with the extensive
use of herbs and spicy peppers one day
when officer come you buy some party and
everybody start coming tchy Staples such
as rice beans corns and yams are widely
used the behem they don't really use a
lot of vegetables and prefer fried food
over cooked or Bo food I think everyone
does fried food is good haian Lego it's
a dish that reflects iian home cooking a
recipe that's passed down in every
Haitian household Janine's recipe
includes beef ribs cow foot and dogs
tail she soaks the meat in lime and
water to reduce any gy
[Music]
flavors then adds flavor with chicken
seasoning a lemon and pepper mixture and
fresh lime
juice add carrot onion celery and bell
pepper to the meat in a separate pot add
papaya chaote and cabbage or any other
vegetable available boil the two Hots
until all the ingredients almost melt
down this will take a few hours in the
meantime I'm hitting up another
spot dun's kitchen the most popular
Haitian restaurant on the island I like
that your waitress is listening to music
and can't be bothered with the the
sounds of reality a place where Haitians
and bahamians commune Under One Roof for
one purpose to eat good ass food that o
that smells good smells like happy juice
it is I'm welcomed by ashin and her
mother shaine with a cup of cremos this
is a popular Haitian drink made from
coconut milk and rum oh wow it's milky
creamy and delicious I Love It dun's
restaurant started recently in 2020 it's
located near the bustling restaurant
District dudun quickly became a favorite
dining destination for both locals and
tourists everything looks stunning in
front of us what is this one within our
culture our national dish is POR Creo
pork Creo starts with seasoned pork
that's boiled for 45 minutes it must be
pre-cooked in order for you to get that
juicy flavor into it because it's pork
and you want it to be able to melt in
your mouth once tender the pork is fried
until it's golden
brown served with fried plantains and
piglets yes so good here there's still
some bone hanging off I'm want to peel
that away breaks off super easily and
there's just a big layer of skin here
skin fat protein everything
together so delicious skin is just
gelatinous oily and there's some
delicious seasonings on here it's so
good thank you and so the people eating
here is it more Haitians or more
bahamians bami e b really love my pork
I've been eating Bahamian food the last
2 days so I can see why the people in
the Bahamas would like it cuz it's
something a little bit familiar but with
the flavor just really Jack turned up
jacked up so I want to try this now this
is like a plantain cup with the same
ingredients stuffed inside but with that
really spicy SLO on top the pork
plantain Bowl is an invention of does
plantain is chopped lightly fried and
flattened mold the flattened plantain
into a bowl and Fry until
golden now fill the edible bowl with the
same delicious pork Creole and
pist M oh it's delicious crunchy starchy
Cup on the outside same tender pork on
the inside and then just this really
sharp slightly sour very spicy slot on
top and it's an edible cup I like edible
dishes oh I got to try more of this part
it's one of the best things I've had on
the island thanks to her
yeah shaine was also a Haitian boat
person she followed her family to the
Bahamas at the age of 16 what do you
think are the biggest challenges for the
Haitian people coming here now residency
citizenship that's definitely at the top
of the
list Haitians coming here illegally are
often left to build their own homes in
improvised Village is known as Shanty
towns I was fortunate to not have grown
in any of those Villages living in a
Shanty Town based on what I've seen
there's no running water there's really
no electricity and it's not a space that
people should live in but it's something
that's better than where they're from
wow so even the shanty town here is
still better than being in Haiti yeah as
Haitian refugees became a crisis in the
1990s the Bahamas started to repatriate
a large number of undocumented Haitians
those who managed to stay struggled to
survive survive in a foreign country
with no Visa meaning no proper job no
accommodation and little acceptance from
locals who felt like their land was
being encroached upon the idea that
there's all these people coming to the
land illegally taking up space in a very
limited Island I could see why that
would put fear into the hearts of some
people and especially if those people
are seem or feel like they're unknown
but the greatest Gateway into getting to
know a new culture or the easiest way is
often through food like oh it's pretty
good maybe I can learn something else
about these Haitian people I would say
yes I would definitely say yes Haitian
food is vastly different from that of
the Bahamas I want to know what folks
here like or don't like about Haitian
food so I'm inviting a Bahamian Chef for
my final climactic meal little backyard
picnic this is real nice Chef siman is a
Bohemian celebrity chef who grew up in
Nassau Chef Simeon is also an
entrepreneur mentor and an author in The
Culinary industry a lot of my Cooks over
the years have been migrants or bamian
Asian when you look at this plate is
there anything familiar here yeah I mean
this use of vegetables and proteins
cooked to the bajas this is definitely
something that I've seen before remember
those two boiling pots we left in
Janine's kitchen they're now so tender
that the veggies could be smashed with a
spoon she adds the mashed vegetables to
the meat pot mixing them
[Music]
well then she serves us up a plate with
rice and black bean sauce I'm want to
grab this I'm going to say the Dan is
probably a
rib wow this is flavorful it took some
time for sure so the pork ribs to me
it's not like they're super tender they
still have some bite to them but I don't
mind them still a nice texture to run
your teeth through them but the flavors
on there it's so Savory but not just
salty there's really like a depth of
flavor there which is fairly different
from the Bahamian food I've tried so far
and this food here you said it pretty
well the pork ribs are not fall off the
bone tender because I think you want to
know it's pork ribs in a whole mash up
of protein this is good I like it it's
tasty food this is definitely somebody's
way of telling their culture through
their plate what does this plate tell
you about Asian
people slow and steady tenacious top
when you need to be yeah here I think I
found a piece of tail so this is Aug
tail it's been hacked up into little
medallions almost the bones in the
middle and then you can just chew around
the
outside oh man that oxtail is delicious
the meat is kind of chewy around the
outside almost like a chicken gizzard it
depends on where you get it on the tail
some are softer and fattier and some are
a little harder right obviously this is
kind of something that they do and eat
regularly that you may not always get
when you go to a version of Haitian
Caribbean Haitian Haitian Bahamian eery
that's very unique this is probably cow
foot heel something or the other heel
right here I'm definitely going to be
chewing for a while but it's good what
do you think Bohemian chefs could learn
from Haitian cocing D flavor
resourcefulness using the whole whole
animal we talk about it now the tail and
all these other stuff we don't use the
whole thing no they use the whole thing
here and that's the kind of food that I
enjoy and this is a story could you
imagine what they would be doing and
talking about as a family if they were
all in a bakia and so as a chef that's
what I try to I want people to have an
experience not just to come sit down eat
and walk away yeah absolutely this I
have never seen before told this is a
gravy y when I sip it it tastes like
liquefied beans beans that's basically
what it is and I'm told we just pour it
over the rice y ooh that looks awesome
it looks like some kind of a thick
chocolate sauce it does not taste like
that though would tastes like liquefied
Black beans with some spices and you
know a couple of things in there and
this is definitely something you can get
at almost every Haitian sport that I do
oh that's awesome do you think the
Haitian food here is affecting the
mainstream food of the
island no not really it's just another
option and it's a good option this is
Caribbean African diaspora for food that
connects all of us and basically when
you eat what do you want you want
delicious food whether that's from this
or that doesn't really ruin anything it
just gives you other things that you can
[Music]
enjoy I understand that Haitians over
Generations have had their own struggles
in coming here and feeling invited and
feeling welcome but it makes me happy to
know that at least through food through
this one small thing that people can
connect with each other 100% we could be
the biggest enemies but we sit down and
we have a food or I introduce you to who
I am through my food there's no way we
won't make small connections food is
fellowship full
stuff our Caribbean culinary Adventure
Continues today I'm escaping the tourist
traps and overpriced drinks and heading
into the bush right now we're on one of
the tiniest airplanes I've ever been on
it feels more like a flying bus it's a
15-minute flight we're going to be
fine this is Andros the the most
sparsely populated island out of 700
islands in the Bahamas the Tranquil
remote island where you explore yourself
every day you find something new that
you want to do do you know what I want
to do today you want to cook right Sun
oh you want to do a challenge right I
saw the challenges I want to
eat tourists here are few and far
between this right here is uh about 10
Tong from 10 sheep in fact you'd be hard
pressed to even find a restaurant and so
what would you say is the Iden of Andros
what makes Andros Andros crabs crabs
crabs crab crab crab crab if you want
food in Andros you've got to get it
yourself no way there's a crab backing
up a
tree how you doing I'm fine where are we
right now we are in the Church of God
Mission House for 20 years Chantel was a
general manager of a briger king in New
Providence now she's chosen the Tranquil
life cooking for church parishioners
inside this Mission house today you're
making sauce am I saying it right yes
sauce sauce it's a traditional Bahamian
stew the flavor of sauce is built on
multiple veggies and herbs including
potatoes onions lime and bay leaves the
protein is up to you this right here is
uh about 10 tongues from 10
sheep these have been boiled already and
then what's the next step you have to
peel the tongue because it has a
layer oh can I see that the inside is
super smooth it looks like a little
foot you could break it in half and
unlike a duck tongue there's no bone
inside it's super soft tender it has
that kind of mtony sheep smell to it
which I like can I give it back sorry I
tore you the that's okay you'd wash your
hands right there
turn all right thanks once the thick
outer skin is removed the tongues are
diced into bite-sized cubes here's what
I can't f figure out we're in the
Bahamas there's not a lot of cattle
hurting growing breeding happening here
so all these tongues have been imported
into the Bahamas giant shipping
containers full of sheep tongues are
coming here why are you Whispering so
much oh you want me to talk I just
whispered because by like if you want to
whisper to but you're like yes that's
what they do next unite the ingredients
in a big pot of clear broth enhance the
flavor with butter chunks salt and
pepper let it simmer until the tongue
meat is tender
PA it with grits to turn it into a
hearty breakfast which doubles as an
efficient hangover
remedy first of all thank you this looks
incredible I've eaten the body of Christ
but not soup or stew would you call this
a stew while you Whispering
again so tell me how we do this I would
normally put some of the sheep down in
first and then add a little bit of the
grit as I eat it joining our table
Emerson a local chef from the island of
Andros I'm going to try a little bit of
this broth
M oh yeah salty peppery and like a nice
layer of fat from whatever meat's been
boiling in there I'm just dying to get a
taste of this
tongue M warm moist it's delicious and
just super tender there's so much tongue
here and I like it there's no skimping
on the tongue some people like it very
very peppery yeah I've learned when
people say pepper here what they really
mean is habanero chili peppers that have
been blend it down that will just
absolutely Scorch your throat what do
you think too much a l
oh I I can smell it from
here we have to start praying soon this
is a place to do it I taste it up into
my nose they normally would say you
haven't tried it unless you put the pepp
in it they like to cry I could so we
like let we hold on spicy little spicy
yeah the heat yeah in the room right no
not the chilies I want to ask both of
you about Andros I spent a few days
already on New Providence and I've
gotten a lot of the tourist experience
and I get here it's completely different
now for you you lived on New Providence
for 20 years now you've come back here
what is the difference between these two
islands what I love the most is peace
but it's not fast it's just laer yes
chef Emerson left Andros at a young age
after spending time in Nassau cooking
inside Resorts he returned back to this
island where he runs a fishing village
with his family and so what would you
say is the identity of Andros what makes
Andros Andros crab crabs crabs crab
Andros is known to have the largest
population of land crabs in the Bahamas
we have two type we call White crabs we
say black crabs the black crabs are the
dark they're lower and then the white
crabs are the bigger version when
they're in season a good crab Hunter
could earn up to $110,000 while only
losing a finger or two they bite very
hard have you been bit before Oh H
scream like a baby oh my God I feel like
you're having a moment right now when
the black ones bite you they don't let
go most of the time you have to beat it
off oh you have to beat it off I don't
even know I have no idea how to beat off
a crab they running a lot in the daytime
but in the night you you have a better
chance of sneaking up on them to get
close enough where it isn't as much back
and forward running crab Hunters here
get busy from late May to early November
when thousands upon thousands of land
crabs litter the streets in search of
spawning grounds that means it might be
tough but it's not too late to catch
some crabs of my
own Emerson junior junior Emerson this
mask is Junior whether he knows it or
not he's my crab Mentor Junior are you
on Bahama's Most Wanted well it's for
protection mosquitoes and prote armed
with only gloves and a flashlight this
season Junior has bagged over 150 dozen
crabs I can't work out the math on that
but it's a lot I don't have any
protective clothing okay here's what I
can do I can I'm going to put my
pants in my
socks that way crab can't go up my pants
are you guys going to do this no I don't
need you yeah you're pretty good the sun
is set we have our gear confident I'm
confident in me H not really but I'm
confident in me there's nothing left to
do but to do
it and are they going to be in a hole or
could they just be laying out well I
hope they're just lying out if I see a
crab I'm going to yell crab okay I'll
yell crab as well I don't want to go
they're
going but I probably should
[Music]
[Applause]
I think I hear one over
[Music]
here no no that's just you
walking any luck no
[Music]
uhuh it's like creating a cool
flare crab crab crab
crab crab oh dude good eye it's a white
crab here but it is at the base of this
tree what do you suggest it's under the
tree well I'm going to run him out out
to the clear and you catch him over
there so I'll go over there yes okay
I'll go over here he's going to he's
going to scar oh is it biging
[Music]
no oh my God the Pinchers okay lay down
little boy they can really poke you with
their back cloths got to pick them up
from side to side oh side to side yes so
you think he can't he can't get me
[Music]
that what's that like buddy is big is
bright is beautiful this is the white
one yes it is beauty big body this
pincher right here this could cut off
your thumb easy you'll see a lot of
people on this island nine fingers
there's a reason for it it's also not
true how do I do you did well for the
first time H do you think it was pretty
unfounded Emerson's lack of confidence
in me I almost lose confidence in you
too because you almost nine
fingers all right in you go plop there
you go let's get some more
crabs crab
crab oh come on were you sleeping buddy
this is too easy oh oh he's pissed I
woke him up from a good dream get him
Sunny get
him oh yeah open the bag hold on let me
check my bpms this is wild
135 oh it's easy with those gloves huh
sunny sunny got one in the tree holy cow
there's a crab backing up a
tree what the heck I've been looking on
the ground this whole time what do you
recommend do I throw a rock at it no
okay oh no he's got a good grip yeah I'm
going to get a stick I'm going to knock
it down you want me jump and CCH it oh
jump you think
jump B oh are you
okay Emon have you ever seen that before
crabs and trees no I've never seen that
have you seen that no that is wild he
did that for you Sunny yeah it did it
for me I think so for the
show watch the Bro Sunny watch the bro
yeah let's see
it oh real quick by the
legs Gentlemen let's see what we got oh
it's heavy this has got to be uh what 10
lb maybe a little more yeah maybe a
little more gentlemen thank you honorary
crb cat now hey I got a surprise for you
what's that you said when you go cobbing
sometime you come up with nine fingers
uh-huh well I happen to have nine oh
[__] is that from a crab no no this
won't be the last time I need to watch
my fingers this is so much easier when I
could just step on that oh my God that
one almost got
me with crabs in hand we'll be feasting
well tonight but first I have some other
unique Foods on this island that I
absolutely must see kle good morning
good morning put her there what's up
just hanging out in your kitchen like
many on this island kley spent few years
studying and working on New Providence
now she's on tranquil Andros taking care
of her parents and working as a private
Chef or catering events yesterday I went
crabbing I caught several crabs no
gloves several crabs right in Andra
today yesterday okay how would everyone
is so doubtful about me catching crabs
that don't sound realistic you know what
I want to do today you want to cook
right Sunny oh you want to do a
challenge right I plus I want to eat
well it's a good time I'm going to do
stew fish for Mom and Dad and you can
join
us for most bahamians a perfect stew
fish is made from grouper or Snapper and
served with Johnny cakes Chef's pick
today hog snapper so what I'm going to
do is go ahead and remove the wings to
further enhance our dish and then after
this we're going to cut it up does this
soup have a boneless option it doesn't
okay have you ever gotten a bone in your
throat we have but that's the trick of
the Johnny Cake it helps to push it
further
back next kishle portions the fish and
marinates it with salt pepper and goat
Pepper or habanero it's eaten in the
morning that's what we normally have
either stew fish or boil fish normally
yes I see four boxes of Cala in your
refrigerator we have kids that's the
difference we have kids in here too
while the fish absorbs those flavors she
prepares a root she Browns flour in a
pan with
oil and adds bay leaves onion and water
it stirred well to form a thick soup
base now lightly fry the fish to give it
a nice Brown coat
drop the fish in the soup and let it
simmer until the fish is tender and
cooked
through and this is the completed
version of our stew fish I'm dying to
try this everything looks fantastic oh
the Johnny cakes so what makes a Johnny
Cake a Johnny Cake noral bread has
leavon this has just bacon powder no
bacon sodas and no eggs or
anything it's warm the butter just melts
into it crunchy on the outside oh it's
so good this is something I guess you
can take with you you'll give me the
recipe definitely or I should bring you
to America please I'm
ready I want to soak up some of this
broth
mhm oh that's so good it reminds me of
when people in the south in the USA they
have biscuits and gravy it has a little
bit of that quality to it where it's a
little peppery it's thick it's Savory
but it's just on another level cuz
there's some spice to it you've added
some Citrus and then right here in the
middle a big old fish filla be mindful
of the bones yeah you got to eat with
caution
mhm okay once you fry it down it helps
to seal the flavors into it oh these
flavors are sealed they're not going
anywhere the fish is flaky sticky and
I'm not used to having fish with this
type of a flavor with kind of a thick
stew is it something you think you'd try
at home yeah if it was available
absolutely but that leads me to my next
question this island is so mysterious to
me because if you go to New Providence
there's restaurants everywhere right but
I come out here I have to come to your
kitchen to experience this how come
there are so few restaurants on this
island almost no restaurants
[Music]
the Bahamas islands are all marketed
differently they Market andr Island for
bone fishing in between the summer
months you see more bone fishing persons
come in that's where I come in I do
private caterings for homeowners coming
in back and forth do you enjoy doing
that I do I can't get to travel to all
of the states in Florida so it's good to
meet somebody else the states travel to
you definitely where are you from
Minnesota that's why you say you're
taking me huh
to thank kley for the breakfast I've
invited her to join our crab Feast later
in the day meantime I'm headed to one of
the only restaurants you'll find on this
island the lucky Lua oh your kitchen is
gorgeous you can double as a a
background for a weatherman yes
hopefully in addition to running lucky
loosa Charlene also cooks for members of
a nearby military base one of her more
notable dishes is a bit of a Caribbean
novelty her stuffed White Crown
pigeon the pigeon it's white the pigeon
is black but only the top of the crown
of the head is white how do you usually
get your hands on the pigeons you go
hunting them hunting season September
29th to October I think 30th otherwise
we cannot shoot them oh it's too late
for that now yeah this dainty bird once
abundant in this area has declined in
numbers as of late now while they're in
season Hunters are limited to 50 Birds
per day which uh still seems like a lot
to me you're serving pigeon but you're
actually stuffing it with a LOF conen
Lobster with bacon
seasoning Charlene starts her dish by
dicing ingredients for the stuffing the
con and lobster gives the stove top
stuffing a zest is that cheating you're
using I can put that away and I can use
my bread Chrome see I'm I'm backed up
you don't need this I don't need that
yeah you're not relying on it I'm not
ring you don't have to use I don't have
to use that at all but you can if you
want to sauté the meat with onion celery
Chili Pepper and a touch of goat pepper
fry the pigeons until they cook
[Music]
through now the stuffing moving with
meticulous Precision she fills the
delicate Birds then stuffs them into the
oven for 30
minutes right here two pigeons maybe
they were siblings I want to jump into
this right here bacon stuffing
Seafood only a hint of stove top
stuffing to be honest I really love
Stove Top Stuffing so you taste the
bacon and then you just taste little
bits of seafood some crunchy conk some
chewy Lobster that's awesome this is a
leg rip that off that's a thigh right
here look at this look how tiny this is
oh there we go that's a bite of meat
super dark
meat so good but there's just not very
much of it right here this is the breast
this is all just meat it's a dark skin
blackish gray almost and then the meat a
slightly bloody gray color it's an
interesting
color delicious juicy a little oily
fatty definitely dark meat so usually if
you're eating chicken the breast meat is
going to be more dry white meat here
it's super juicy super fatty which I
like lobster conk inside a pigeon super
unique but not the last food we have for
today the crabs we caught yesterday are
waiting for me at Lorie's house and this
is Lori she is Chef Emerson's
Aunt Lori we're here thank you for
having me can you believe I help catch
some of these oh wow you did yeah oh
okay why why is everybody laughing at
that idea usually freshly caught crabs
don't hit the pot right away many locals
have one of these in their backyard a
crab pen where crabs are fed fresh fruit
allowing them to purge whatever nasty
stuff they've been eating on the forest
floor the result is supposed to be
sweeter less bitter meat when the crabs
are ready they need to be click now you
know they're very aggressive sometimes
they they don't like to be C I think
that one's sleeping oh there sleeping
and this is a big one I'm going to try
to get the Clippers like that and then
I'm going to ring
it like
that and it's easy to just once you do
it right you just rip its arms off yes I
did cool and then right in the joint you
clip and it just drops right
off joint drops right
off it's an easy fix yeah sorry I just
if you know what you're doing
okay
that okay you want to hold it yeah it's
like the knight from Monty Python it has
no arms and no legs yeah it's still
alive yes it's still alive but in our
culture we clip them first before
preparing them I feel it moving its
little Nubs it's like I'm trying to walk
but nothing's happening yes everything
is going all right I'm going to put that
one oh my God you almost that one almost
got me okay you know what I felt bad for
like 2 seconds why don't you try to get
one that's as sleep no cuz that one
tried to attack me it's personal okay
the hardest part is taking off the claw
yeah sorry I'm going to bruise our food
oh this is so much easier when I could
just step on them I can't step on them
right now you try to pull it out pull by
the big claw yeah
quickly just pull it
quickly yeah good there you go yeah get
up get up get up oh what are you going
to do with your little ass clo okay yeah
sunnyome um I just I just Twisted oh try
to get it by B Claws and then um twist
it I feel bad for
it oh you pluged it gone give it a
little bit of a Twist good yeah there we
go that's stressful I mean the CL oh huh
what was I so freaked out about look at
this today Lori is making another bamian
classic crab and dough the amputated
crabs are cleaned and placed in a
pot seasoned with salt and pepper onion
and gold pepper add a cup of water and
let it
steam in the meantime prepare a dough
with flour baking powder salt and
water and place that over the
crab let the pot boil steaming the bread
and the crabs for 25
minutes now it's time to
eat honey you might as well take this
big bite of here cuz it's easyest I
could okay I'll dough it's a little
different from the Johnny Cake sorry I
started I mean go ahead don't wait for
me but you have to wait for the crab fat
inside all the crab together turn it
over so it doesn't do oh so it's like
the head becomes a bowl and just pull it
apart it's like dark and brown in there
yeah I sopped up a ton of this fat it's
wet it's
brown yeah that's a lot of flavor it's
super fatty it's a little sweet but it's
also a little bitter too and this bread
is outstanding it's soft and doughy like
my pack abs then the other experience
comes from the opposite side of the crab
this piece is called the band you pull
this band completely off oh you're so
good at crab anatomy andr it's our thing
now see this we're going to break it in
half we're going to take these off
individually we just bite into it a
challeng just bite in it awesome wao
that's a huge chunk and that chunk of
meat is better than the F no
bitterness yeah just super sweet awesome
delicious and you know in the US a few
people appreciate the crabs body you go
to bread Lobster you get crab legs and
that's it but here you can see there's a
bunch of meat there's fat there's a lot
in there that is easily wasted I'll see
this take the chor you try to separate
this from that see wow now pull it out
pull it out
slowly right he's got it ow
[Music]
yes I can see you enjoy that yes you can
now be labeled as andran cuz youve
officially eaten the crab
oh my gosh that's the best bite so far
super meaty sweet delicious so You' have
experienced crab and dough to me when I
first came to this island I was a little
bit skeptical about andos we were trying
to contact people it was very hard to
contact people to know what was going on
here it just seemed like this place
where you just have to go here to figure
things out and then even once we got
here it's like interesting it's a a
different pace of life it's very
different from the capital city and I
can see why people appreciate that but
what I appreciate even more than any of
that is that this place is so rich and
abundant with food I mean the fact that
we're eating a delicious crab meal and
you can just walk out in the forest and
crab this from the bush to the plate
yeah so this place is just so rich with
resources and natural beauty and
wonderful people too thank you to andas
this is just water
and oh [__] if I see a crab I'm going to
yell a crab some may see the Bahamas as
a money trap overrun with tourists do
you have a conk yes I say in the Bahamas
you'll find whatever you're looking for
oh I hear a Bo let's go let's go let's
go our Caribbean culinary Adventure
Continues here on the Bahamas sparsely
populated Andros Island today we're
taking hunting to a whole new level the
forest here is really thick if we go in
the forest how are you going to get
through in this tourist driven country
country I'm about to experience what no
traveler has experienced before what is
the most dangerous part of what we're
doing today you might come across a big
male one sometime they try run from the
dog and they run into you you're getting
attacked by the boy yeah and it all
starts here sir good morning good
morning sir Jerome geran this is
fantastic we're on a beach right now in
Andros Island in the Bahamas today we're
going to do something special we're
going after a board today going try to
catch something I hope so or else we got
no video yo why do
I do it for job if we catch one say
about 100 lb we going to sell them for
200 or 150 you sell the meat sell the
meat I wanted to ask about how you do
this cuz when I was in Alabama I went
hog hunting and I had a deer rifle and I
drove around on a golf cart until we
found some Hogs to shoot here's a
completely different story here you're
hunting with dogs how do they know if
they're hunting or just going out to you
know be taken to the bathroom they know
what they doing I start putting on my
hunting clothes they know what's going
on
it's challenging it's risky it's not for
the faint of heart here the plan will go
like this the hunter releases his dogs
the dogs search for a scent and track
down a wild hog when they find one they
pit it down until the hunter catches up
and finishes the
job so where do I come in today how can
I help I like could give you a chance to
take the ball from them what is this for
put tie the legs together just that yeah
I thought you're using a gun I don't
like hunt with guns you've never been
bit no I don't freid them at all so
today I don't have a knife I don't have
a gun we're going to hunt down a wild
boar and I'm armed with this I just want
to make that clear to
[Music]
everybody we are on our way to the
hunting spot I've got my piece of string
with me that's my weapon today I got a
mask and gloves why do I need a mask now
going protect you from mosquitoes I'm
not I don't need protection from
mosquitoes we're freaking hunters and
gatherers but mostly Hunters
Andros Island runs about 100 m by 45 Mi
although the island has a distinct
outline it is highly fragmented it's a
flat heavily forested Island which makes
it the perfect home for wild boar dogs
are coming off oh [__] they're taking
off Jerome has been hunting wild boore
in Andros for over 30 years oh [__] he's
trained over 25 dogs rotating them for
each hunt today we've got Lacy jet Dex
and Max are they hunting or playing they
just seem like they're having a good
time that one's taking a
piss still sniffing M they're going in
here
now these are a cur type dogs bred in
the USA known for their incredible
tracking ability in the right conditions
they can follow a scent for Miles Jerome
where you at where's Jerome
Jerome where's anybody
I'm going to scroll Instagram till
someone calls me and tells me what to do
ah Gary ve
inspirational man I saw about 10 the
small ones oh piglets yeah and then two
big ones they went oh our whole family
maybe they're on a
picnic an invasive species with no
natural Predators wild Boors are
destructive beasts destroying crops and
the homes of wildlife by trampling and
brooding they can eat anything they mate
like crazy and they're impossible to
make extinct so if you feel bad that
these animals are being
hunted you shouldn't plus a wild boar
paired with the right Chef will make for
one of the best dinners of your summer
but before we eat we've got a lot of
work to do he some big truck how do you
know it's a pig track and not a dog
track see the the pig and
how dog and how like you know yeah
that's the pig TR oh man I would have
completely missed that yeah according to
Jerome this is a spot where pigs likely
pass through to drink fresh water early
this morning right no a hog could be
anywhere in this area that's what I'm
hoping the dogs lead the way looking for
a scent to chase down look at this one
over here is not hunting at all go hunt
get a
pig our job is to follow and not lose
them the dogs just went into their
easier said than done if you lose them
or in my case when we lose them is there
anything in here you either e follow
your gut or hope they call
out watch your
[Music]
eyes right now we're listening this
whole thing is tough I don't see the
science behind it I don't know the
strategy it's like sometimes he leads
sometimes the dogs lead but this is not
easy work at
all this is exactly what the wild Boors
want
our pack is divided and already in
disarray this Forest is super thick Pig
can get through here easy five times
faster than the human probably twice as
fast as a dog so that's why he needs
four of
them right now we're just
listening see if anything's
rustling see if any dogs
bark but once
again nothing
in the world of hunting wind is
everything it can hide or expose you
before you're even with an ey shot too
much wind can mean the dogs won't be
able to accurately follow as scent for
long if I'm being honest I don't think
it's in the cards for today
so bad news hunting is highrisk high
reward today more on the risk side we
went out for a few hours tried our best
nothing and I don't know how it works
exactly cuz the dogs just kind of run
around sometimes it seems like they're
going after something sometimes it seems
like they're just playing and having a
good time he's not really communicating
with the dogs sometimes he's following
them sometimes they're following him I'm
not sure like how organized and process
this is I would say it's more of an art
than a science maybe it's just luck I
don't know we don't have a por but I
think we can order a
por we still need a video so I think we
should have done this from the beginning
it was my fault it's my mistake but we
shouldn't be out here hunting following
dogs around trying to lasso Pigs by
their feet no instead we're going to do
it the smart way have someone bring a
boar to us like Uber Eats but with live
animals I'm not sure who's bringing it
but someone is going to bring a wild
boar we're going to eat some wild boar
today gosh dang it all
right you can't win them all
[Music]
one across the R Bo
all right I was told he just found a pig
oh I hear it
oh holy oh it's
huge approaching the boar it's
surrounded by four dogs but all it would
take is one swift movement for it to
slip away I know that speed is essential
and I'm not going to let a little thing
like having no idea what I'm doing stop
me from committing 100% to this moment I
got my string
yeah holy sh I grabed The Boar's back
leg because it's the farthest from its
teeth then I try to flip it over to
break its leverage I remember something
about a string and tying it
up that that huh we don't yeah great
show me how to tie
it don't break your WR too much pressure
on him yeah yeah uhhuh put underneath
there and set it okay double it yeah now
have to put this in you do the same
thing oh tie it twice mhm turns out you
don't tie the back legs together it's
front back front back now we fliping
more if it's not tight it takes no time
for the board to turn and Jet same with
that got
it
woo my man yeah how'd you guys do it we
foot up you went your own way I hear you
yelling I hear the pig I hear dogs
barking we come here what happened he
was in the road sitting down and when
the dog ran through he was like oh let
this be the one let this be the one and
all of a sudden I two the dogs was true
first at first and then the other two
went through after they he those two
back in and then we went through and we
had a pig start squealing when we get
there there was a WR she tried to fight
but you know she couldn't win that
battle dogs are okay yeah oh they look
proud and tired they always surprised me
yeah they look cute and fluffy until
it's time for Action then the dogs got
real vicious real quick
yeah hey good job yeah what's next how
do you carry it from
here holy
[Music]
[__] hunting doesn't give out merit
badges or trophies for doing your best
either you eat or you don't some may say
that in this modern world hunting is a
vestage of a less civilized
past but Jerome who feeds his family by
tracking hunting and selling boore meat
he would have to dis
[Music]
agree with the Bor and toe plans for a
major Feast have begun soon this animal
will feed dozens of locals in the
[Music]
[Applause]
community you're feeling something you
can't
explain you to start Jerome boils a
large pot of
water dipping the hug in then scraping
away it hair and outer layer of
[Music]
skin he collects the B's internal
organs finally it's sectioned into
smaller pieces and left it boil for an
hour it down while it boils we're
heading to a nearby Beach for another
special daring Tropical
Treat Solomon put it there Hey brother
do you know what I like about barracudas
you don't have to track them down in the
goddamn Forest ah boy I know what you
mean Barracuda is a long thin and
ferocious looking fish living near the
coast in subtropical Seas I tried it
once in Mexico
City here in the Bahamas in no uncertain
terms it is advised that you only eat
this fish at your own risk well they eat
something of the reef something that's
called Cera it's actually natural toxins
that built up from algae that smaller
fish of around the reefs eat and then
these being the Predator fish they eat
those fish and that's how they get
contaminated I've been told in the
Bahamas it's kind of a right of passage
to eat the Barracuda it means that
you're not afraid you're ready to take
on the risk of potentially poisoning
yourself you're taking on the risk of
death all right I'll do it Solomon is a
fisherman and fishing guy for dudes who
boat shoes and sweater vests oh wow I'm
not sure that I'm sitting in the right
area with years of seafood catching and
eating experience I hope he chose the
right one we kind of tell too sometimes
is you watch the natural stuff again so
if the Flies don't come it's
poison are you also saying that anything
a fly lands on is something you would
eat that's a good question is
[Laughter]
it colon cisis Barracuda making two
giant
fillets he cleans it then cuts it into
bite-sized pieces before applying his
own seasoning
blend it's shallow fried in hot oil on
both sides until it's golden
brown it's hot juicy and most likely
poison free Solomon yes this is a big
moment there were flies landing on this
Barracuda which we've established is a
good thing so if it's poisonous I'm
going to know pretty soon we're on
there's no hospital no if you get poison
you have to go online book an airplane
ticket get a PCR test go at 5:00 a.m.
get on the plane you're
dead I can feel the outside it feels a
little bit crispy I can feel the
seasoning kind of baked in there let's
try it
out that is delicious I'm a great fan of
Bara man this is so different from other
fried fish I think a lot of fried fish
really depends on a huge flaky crunchy
batter and sometimes it's more batter
than actual fish then people are
smothering it tartar sauce and it's like
there was no point in having the fish in
the first place here there's no like big
thick batter on there just a little bit
of a crunch and a ton of fresh fish and
delicious seasoning where did you learn
this recipe I do a lot of cooking so you
know you get to experiment with stuff
and works out you keep it if it doesn't
show out the doll that's why I like
about everybody on this island they find
a way to make it work and a lot of
people are getting their own food you're
getting your own fish the other day I
got my own crabs today we got a boar and
so everybody's figuring out everybody
has their own ways their own Traditions
or their own twist on the tradition when
they cook food yes so far so good so
good I see Still Standing I think no
issue not at
all back to the boore after boiling for
an hour it's brought to Mount Pleasant
fishing Village Jerome and Jon woke up
at 3:00 a.m. this morning so they've
decided to duck out early but not before
rewarding their dogs with some bore meat
now it's all Emerson who we met in our
last video I got no grief I got no on my
hands he's a trained je who decided to
settle on Andros to enjoy a more
tranquil lifestyle after years of
working in the Bahamas Hotel industry
today he's cooking this boar into
several dishes culminating in a
community Feast first up grilled boar
ribs the ribs are boiled with herbs and
spices to tenderize the meat before it's
marinated in Emerson's secret homemade
barbecue sauce a sauce so secret he
won't tell me what's in it toss it on an
open fire and Grill to perfection
my ever Sunny bore Chev extraordinaire
is this your first board actually the
first one we got in a while brought out
there but I could b in a hotels do you
think there's going to be a difference
between the wild boar and a domesticated
Bo yeah normally they do days a little
different with the natural B they have
like a more natural flavor better all
right let's
[Music]
see oh man that's so delicious sweet
Tangy barbecue sauce is coming it's just
quite tender actually oh there we go I
got another piece right here boiling I
think is really render down the fat a
bit and then it's just a nice crisp on
the outside every time I eat a wild
boore I feel like the the texture of the
fat is a little bit different there's
just something like bubbly and a little
bit unusual about the fat I think it's
what they eat the native food I think
that really play a big role in it it's
hard to believe that just a couple hours
ago I had my KN on this boy's neck and
man it was completely worth it
dinner is almost ready Emerson's
finishing up with the starter B soup he
Sears the bore meat in hot oil then adds
homemade broth that bubbles up along
with onions carrots Irish potatoes and
cassaba he seasoned with salt pepper
lime and bay leaves time to
eat as the dinner bell rings out members
of the community trickle in to share in
this celebration Lori the crab killer
from our last video also joins us our
hunter today he actually went home
already cuz he's been up since 3:00 a.m.
he and his dogs are tired but the dogs
did get to eat some of the pork before
they left I want everyone to know
uhuh gor yes have you had wild boar
before yes I have but not like this
first time first time let's try it home
this is beautiful big fatty pieces of
pork
nice M soft feeling I would say yeah
that's delicious the best part is the
fat the fat actually has an outstanding
texture it almost tastes like soft meat
what is that gavo that's another
Bohemian specialty love gavo that's
delicious it's Savory peppery juicy pork
vegetables are perfect not mushy this is
like perfectly
ente what is this one the pepper pepper
pork it's basically a stewed pork dish
made with onions potatoes plantains
Tomatoes bell peppers herbs and lime
juice plus the Bor meat which has
already been seasoned with salt and
pepper Add Water butter seal it up and
let it steam this is so good big
beautiful chunks of
pork M I love the gravy the consistency
of the gravy mhm very tomatoey it's got
some pop that's what I like about food
here a little bit of goat pepper a
habanero a little bit of heat but not
too much Emerson you cook this whole
thing by yourself that's sir that's wild
I want to try this liver right here
scoop that on my plate saute liver with
carrots peppercorns vinegar onion sweet
pepper and garlic I'm ready to try the
liver because I have never done so
before oh it's delicious it's like
classic liver and onion M it's something
I never really ate growing up but I love
it beautifully sauteed Savory soft
you're a great chef thank you sir so it
seems that the crabbing is just a lot
easier right catching a wild boar real
hard so what part did you do let's be
honest the dogs they're doing all the
work yes of course you know people
always talk about organic but then those
same people don't like hunting but this
is an organic Pig it's basically like a
Whole Food's Pig it's chilling out in
the mangroves it's eating orange is it's
very healthy and this is the way our
forefathers live by hunting and going
out in the sea and catching their meals
you know they go to the store and B the
meals they actually went out there and
they hunted or they
fished oh [__] if I see a crab I'm going
to y a crab some may see the Bahamas as
a money trap overrun with tourists do
you have a conk yes I say in the Bahamas
you'll find whatever you're looking for
while you disembark your cruise ship and
suck down a multitude of Bahama Mamas
just know that there's another side to
this island beyond the resorts beyond
the sandy beaches aside that few
visitors have a chance to see and if you
ever get the chance to experience the
Bahamas behind the curtain well it's
absolutely worth
it and that wraps up our Bahamas
Adventure five videos in 5 days I want
to say a huge thank you to all the
different chefs and local people who
contributed to this video today and
throughout this series including
Atlantis on Paradise Island I had a
blast getting to know more about the
Bahamas and the unique food and people
here and I hope you enjoyed it too
that's it for this one thank you so much
for watching I'll see you next time a
peace what do you guys think of the Hat
keep the Hat get rid of the Hat it's do
you notice it's a bandana hat it's you
get what I was doing there